A Guide to the Louis J. Halle, Jr. Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10603-c
Louis J. Halle, Jr. Papers 1915-1985
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10603-c
ca. 8,000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the Library by Mr. Louis J. Halle, Jr. of Geneva, Switzerland on December 30, 1985.
Biographical Sketch
(see attached entries from Who's Who in America, 1986-1987, 44th edition, Vol. I, p. 1161, and Contemporary Authors New Revision Series, Vol. 2, p. 291.)
Scope and Content
This collection of ca. 8,000 items (25 Hollinger boxes; 8 shelf feet), 1915-1985, consisting of the correspondence, articles, book reviews, lecture notes, and miscellanea of Louis J. Halle, Jr., of Geneva, Switzerland, reflects the versatility and depth of his career and personal interests as a writer, teacher, naturalist, and expert on international relations.
Louis J. Halle, Jr. maintained two types of correspondence files, alphabetical by last name of correspondent and topical (or subject) files. Both contain a wide variety of subjects and correspondents, and will be cited in an index at the end of this guide according to the box and folder number where they can be found. Subjects of a folder are distinguished from correspondents by use of an asterisk attached to all subject entries, such as nuclear war* 2.6 which would be found in folder 6 of box 2. Correspondents with their own files include: Dean Acheson, Bill Bundy, Kenneth Ford, George Kennan, Charlton Ogburn, Urs Schwarz, and Kenneth Thompson.
Several of the topical files deal with the magazines that frequently published Louis J. Halle, Jr. 's articles, such as the Virginia Quarterly Review, The New Republic, Audubon Magazine, National Geographic, British Birds, and The New York Times, and two of his publishers, Houghton Mifflin and Princeton University Press. He also has files concerning individual books: The Nature of Ideology(published as The Ideological Imagination), The Cold War as History, Out of Chaos, The Sea and the Ice, Elements of International Strategy, The Society of Man, Sedge, Spring in Washington, and Hamlet/ Odysseus/ The Passing of Arthur/ Anthony and Cleopatra (published as The Search For the Eternal Norm).
The collection also contains two nature diaries; The Sea and the Ice Antarctic diary and his notes on his visits to the Shetlands in 1968, 1970, and 1972.
Other general topics in the subject files include: discussions concerning all aspects of ornithology, United States foreign policy, American history, science, philosophy, the writer's relationship with his publisher, outer space colonization, wildlife conservation, nuclear weapons, and politics.
The lecture and article series include: ad-hoc lectures, lectures concerning " America and the World Since 1945" given at the Bologna Center of the Johns Hopkins University, "A Layman's Guide to Nuclear Power," a lecture concerning the "Role of Concepts in International Relations," miscellaneous book reviews, lectures, and talks, newspaper articles, notes, ideas, fragments, miscellaneous printed articles, a seminar on strategic studies regarding the concept of a limited war in the nuclear age, and "Truth, Freedom and the Academic Vocation."
Organization
This collection arrived in good order at the Library in European classeurs and manila envelopes, with the contents of each clearly labeled by the donor. Those files pertaining to a single subject are in reverse chronological order and those containing alphabetical correspondence are arranged by the last name of the correspondent, thus preserving the original order imposed by Mr. Louis J. Halle, Jr..
The three series established for these papers are: 1) Alphabetical Correspondence, 2) Topical Correspondence, and 3) Lectures and Articles, although some lectures and articles are scattered throughout the collection.
Item Listing
- SERIES I: ALPHABETICAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence - A, 1958-1972 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Dean Acheson, 1952-1982; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Ba-Bon, 1950-1982 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Boo-Buz, 1953-1979 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - C, 1947-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - D-E, 1958-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence - F, 1955-1984 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Foreign Affairs & Bill Bundy, 1971-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Kenneth Ford, 1972-1983; (3 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - G, 1953-1983 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Ha, 1952-1984 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - He-Hu, 1949-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence of the Halle family, 1915-1983 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - I, 1974-1981 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - J, 1952-1984 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence - K, 1949-1984 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence with George Kennan, 1964-1984 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - L, 1955-1980 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - M, 1950-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence - N-P, 1952-1983 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Charlton Ogburn, 1983-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Charlton Ogburn, 1948-1982; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - Q-R, 1948-1983 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - Sa-So, 1955-1985 (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence - St, 1956-1979 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Urs Schwarz, 1962-1985; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence - T, 1954-1982 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Kenneth W. Thompson, 1957-1985; (2 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence - U-V, 1963-1966 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence - Wa, 1947-1977 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence - We-Wy, 1955-1977 (Box Box 7)
- SERIES II: TOPICAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence with the American Foreign Service Journal, 1954-1955 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Audubon Magazine, 1964-1977, 1985; (5 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Audubon Naturalist Society of the Central Atlantic States, 1975-1982 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Audubon Naturalist Society, 1958-1974 (Box Box 9)
  - Correspondence re Lectures given at the Bologna Center of the Johns Hopkins University, 1979-1980 (Box Box 9)
  - Correspondence with British Birds, 1961-1984 (Box Box 9)
  - Papers re the career of Louis Halle, Jr., 1941-1960; (2 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Chatto & Windus re The Cold War as History, 1965-1971 (Box Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Harper & Row re The Cold War as History, 1965-1971 (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence re Miscellaneous Options and the Index of The Cold War as History, 1966-1970 (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence re Opinions & Criticisms of The Cold War as History, 1965-1968 (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence & Notes re The Cold War as History, 1965-1966 (Box Box 10)
  - Notes re The Cold War as History, ca. 1963-1965 (Box Box 10)
  - Ditchley Meeting re Strategic Studies, 1972 (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence re "1898: The United States in the Pacific", 1955-1956 (Box Box 11)
  - Correspondence re Elements of International Strategy, 1980-1982 (Box Box 11)
  - Material for a volume of essays in historiography, 1965-1969 (Box Box 11)
  - Graduate Institute of International Studies, 1956-1985; (3 folders) (Box Box 11)
  - Exchanges with the Student Association of the Graduate Institute of International Studies, 1974 (Box Box 11)
  - Correspondence with Edmund Gullion and the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, 1966-1975; (2 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Correspondence on Hamlet/Odysseus/The Passing of Arthur/Anthony and Cleopatra, 1967-1980; (2 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Correspondence with Houghton Mifflin Company, 1976-1985; (2 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Correspondence with Houghton Mifflin Company, 1970-1976 (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence re Bob Klein and his book Sovereign Equality Among States, 1962-1974, 1985; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence with National Geographic Society, 1981-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence re The Nature of Ideology published as The Ideological Imagination, 1971-1975; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - Correspondence re The Nature of Ideology published as The Ideological Imagination, 1970-1971 (Box Box 14)
  - Correspondence with The New Republic, 1962-1975; (4 folders) (Box Box 14)
  - Correspondence with The New Republic, 1957-1961; (3 folders) (Box Box 15)
  - Correspondence and Articles for the New York Times, 1961-1975; (3 folders) (Box Box 15)
  - Correspondence and Articles for the New York Times, 1954-1960; (2 folders) (Box Box 16)
  - Lt. Calley article for the New York Times, 1971 (Box Box 16)
  - Reviews & Correspondence re On Facing the& 1985 World, 1947-1951, 1985 (Box Box 16)
  - Correspondence & Source Materials re Out of Chaos, 1969-1978 (Box Box 16)
  - Reviews & Correspondence re the British publication of Out of Chaos, 1974-1978 (Box Box 16)
  - Correspondence with Princeton University Press, 1955-1980; (5 folders) (Box Box 17)
  - Program for Strategic and International Security Studies (P.S.I.S.), 1979-1984 (Box Box 17)
  - Correspondence & Articles re the Protection of Nature, 1961-1970 (Box Box 18)
  - "The Question of Commitment", 1972-1974 (Box Box 18)
  - Correspondence with Scott Meredith Literary Agency and John Brockman Associates, 1982-1983 (Box Box 18)
  - Correspondence with Houghton Mifflin Company re The Sea and the Ice (American edition), 1971-1980 (Box Box 18)
  - Correspondence with Michael Joseph LTD re The Sea and the Ice (English edition), 1971-1978 (Box Box 18)
  - Reviews of The Sea and the Ice, 1972-1977 (Box Box 18)
  - Correspondence re The Sea and the Ice, 1971-1972 (Box Box 18)
  - Correspondence with Audubon re The Sea and the Ice, 1971-1973 (Box Box 19)
  - Correspondence with readers of the Audubon issue on Antarctica, 1973-1974 (Box Box 19)
  - The Sea and the Ice Antarctic Diary, 1970-1971 (Box Box 19)
  - Correspondence & Notes re the Antarctic Venture, 1969-1971 (Box Box 19)
  - Correspondence re the Security Issue, 1954-1955 (Box Box 19)
  - Correspondence re Sedge, 1959-1964 (Box Box 19)
  - Notes & Correspondence re Shetland Visits, 1968-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 20)
  - Correspondence re The Society of Man, 1963-1969; (2 folders) (Box Box 20)
  - Correspondence re Space-colonization, 1978-1980 (Box Box 20)
  - Correspondence re Spring in Washington, 1947-1956 (Box Box 20)
  - Correspondence re Spring in Washington, 1945-1947 (Box Box 21)
  - Correspondence re Symposium on "What is Happening in Soviet Russia?", 1956 (Box Box 21)
  - Letters to the Times Literary Supplement, 1965-1980 (Box Box 21)
  - University of Virginia Projects & Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box Box 21)
  - Correspondence with The Virginia Quarterly Review, 1963-1985; (2 folders) (Box Box 21)
- SERIES III: LECTURES & ARTICLES
  - Ad-hoc Lectures, 1950-1984; (4 folders) (Box Box 22)
  - Lectures re "America and the World Since 1945" given at the Bologna Center of the Johns Hopkins School, 1980 (Box Box 22)
  - Lectures re American Foreign Policy given at the Bologna Center of the Johns Hopkins School, 1978-1979; (4 folders) (Box Box 23)
  - A Layman's Guide to Nuclear Power; The Human Nature of International Conflict, 1972-1974 (Box Box 23)
  - Lectures re the Role of Concepts in International Relations, 1958-1959; (2 folders) (Box Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Book Reviews, 1954-1956 (Box Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Lectures and Talks, 1955-1959, 1966, 1971 (Box Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Articles, 1950-1982 (Box Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Ideas, & Fragments, 1952-1955 (Box Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Halle Articles, 1938-1984; (3 folders) (Box Box 25)
  - Seminar "Strategic Studies" at the Graduate Institute of International Studies, 1970-1975 (Box Box 25)
  - "Truth, Freedom, and the Academic Vocation," A Valedictory Lecture at the Graduate Institute of International Studies, 1974 (Box Box 25)